discalm
斬る  何をですか
人を… だろ
九十九斬りの恋川春菊
ただ 斬りまくっていたら こうなっちまっただけだ
I just kept killing and this is how I ended up.
本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
Killing? Killing what?
People...
Right?
The Killer of 99, Koikawa Shungiku.
Tsukishima, it isn't happening...
月島 あんたには無理よ
As it is, I'm amazed you were able
to get this rock all the way here.
ってか よく１人で こんな岩 運んできたわね
If I'm going to be fighting bugs,
I've gotta be able to cut this!
これくらい斬らねばならないのです  蟲を相手にするには
And also so Mugai-dono accepts me!
無涯殿に認められるためにも
The best thing for a hangover is more drink!
やっぱ 迎え酒は効くな
I got a nosebleed!
鼻血 出ただろうが
うわっ ちょっ… ちょっと
H-Hey!
That cut was so clean, it shines like a mirror!
鏡のような切り口 一点の曇りもない太刀筋
His stance was perfect...
しかも あんな刃こぼれした刀で
Even using a beat-up, old katana like that!
Koikawa-dono, please train
me in the art of the blade!
恋川殿 この月島仁兵衛の師匠になってください
What's this about, new kid?
おい おい いきなりだな 新入り
How can I learn to cut a rock that way?
どうやったら あんなふうに岩を斬れるんですか
岩？ ああ あれか なんてことはねえ
A rock?
Oh, that...
Nothing to it.
コンニャクだと思えばいいんだ
Just approach it like a konjac yam.
なんと コンニャクですね
What?
Konjac, you say?
コンニャクは硬いです
Konjac is very hard.
コンニャクなわけねえだろ
It isn't konjac, you stupid kid.
The Killer of 99,
Koikawa Shungiku!
See you later.
では
ええ
人斬りだ
Murderer...
九十九斬りの春菊だぞ
It's the Killer of 99, Shungiku.
Why are you even alive?
なんで おめえが のうのうと生きてやがんだ
この大罪人め
You criminal!
出てけ
やめとけ 新入り
Stop it, kid.
It's only natural for them to
want to throw rocks at me.
おりゃな 石をぶつけられて当然なんだ
わかったろ 俺と一緒にいると
Got it?
Hang around me and all of Edo will hate you, too.
おめえも江戸の嫌われもんになっちまうぜ
なんたって 俺は人斬りだからな
I am a murderer.
いいえ 一度師匠と決めたからには
No!
Now that I've chosen you as my master,
my duty is to follow you everywhere.
どこまでもついていくのが弟子の務め
出てけ この野郎
あの方々は
Who are those guys?
火付け盗賊改方さ
火付盗贼改方：取缔纵火、盗窃、赌博等重罪的警官
Arson and theft investigators.
連続強盗事件の捜査に駆り出されたんだろう
They're looking into those serial robberies.
Burglaries?
というと
このあたりの金持ちや商家ばっか狙う強盗事件だ
The houses of local merchants and
of the rich have been robbed.
What's interesting is how it's being pulled off.
おもしれえことに その手口ってのがよ
壁や鉄の扉をすっぱりと斬っちまうんだよ
They cut cleanly through walls or iron doors.
ほぅ よくご存じですね 恋川殿
I'm impressed that you know this, Koikawa-dono.
そりゃあ 俺がやったからな
Well, I was the one who did it...
な なんと
Wh-What?!
冗談に決まってるだろ 強盗なんかしねえよ
That was a joke, kid.
I wouldn't steal.
ただし 人斬りはするがな
However,
I would kill.
うん  さあて 本日も見回り終了
Our patrol's done for the day.
じゃあ 俺はひとりで飲みにいくから
I'm going to go drink alone.
あとは好きにしろ
You do what you like.
ならば 自分も同行して…
Then I'll go with you—
ぜってえ来んな
Don't even think about it!
See you around, kid.
じゃあな あばよ
Oharu-dono, may I have some more?
お春殿 おかわりをお願いしてもよろしいでしょうか
Sure!
は～い！仁兵衛様
Jinbei-sama,
どんどんおかわりしてくださいね
order as much as you like.
はぁ よく食べるね あのお侍は
That samurai eats a lot.
もう 上新粉が切れてしまったよ
We're out of the good rice.
Then go and get some more.
じゃあ おじいちゃん 買ってきて
Huh?
だって 仁兵衛様には もっともっと活躍していただかないといけないんだから
We need Jinbei-sama to
keep fighting bugs for us.
お春はあのお侍にずいぶんと親身だね
You've become very close to him.
お春もそんな恋する年ごろになったのかの
So, are you at the age when you fall in love?
Oh, Grandpa!
もう おじいちゃんったら
うわ 危ない
That's dangerous...
Magistrates
御用 御用 伊勢屋に強盗だ
The magistrates are here!
There was a robbery in Iseya!
な なんと
Wh-What?
何見てんだよ
What are you looking at?
Kodenma Prison
お待ちください
Wait!
どうか 恋川殿を今すぐ出してください
Please release Koikawa-dono!
What are you talking about?
貴様 何を言っているんだ
恋川が血刀をひっさげて現場にいるのを見たであろう
You saw him at the crime scene,
with a bloodstained katana.
しかし 恋川殿は罪を認めておりません
But he hasn't admitted his guilt!
あそこにいた理由も話さないのは罪を認めたも同然
If he won't tell us why he was there,
then essentially, he has.
しかし 恋川殿は絶対にやってないんです
But he didn't do it!
自分は信じてます
I believe in him!
Hey, is he serious?
おいおい こいつ マジかよ
How could he believe in a guy like that?
なんで あんな奴をそこまで信じるんだ
目を覚ますことだ 蟲方の新入り
I know you're new to the
Insect Magistrate's Office, but you should wake up.
He's a criminal who's done
many evil things in Edo.
あいつは この江戸で さんざん悪事を働いた大罪人だ
人斬りはいつまでたっても人斬りよ
A murderer will always be a murderer!
小鳥殿
Kotori-dono!
Use your authority to get
Koikawa-dono out of prison!
蟲奉行所の権限ですぐに恋川殿を牢から出すように
火盗改の方々に言ってください
Tell them to release him!
すぐ出られるわけないじゃない
He can't be released so quickly.
な なんと
Wh-What?
とにかく 犯行現場にいた理由を
For one thing, we don't know
春菊君がなんで黙秘してるのかがわからない
why he refuses to tell us
the reason he was there.
ほんとにやったのかもしれないわ
It's possible he did it.
火鉢殿
Hibachi-dono!
釈放してもらうにしても
Even if we had him released,
蟲奉行所も役所の一つ いろいろと手続きが必要なんだ
the Insect Magistrate is a bureaucracy, too.
There's a lot of paperwork.
すぐにとはいかないよ
It wouldn't be quick.
お二人の意地悪
You two are so mean!
恋川殿はやっていません
Koikawa-dono didn't it!
あっ 仁兵衛君
Wait, Jinbei-kun!
どうせ意地悪ですよ
We're just a pair of meanies, anyway.
春菊君も なんで理由を言わないんだろうね
And why do you suppose
Shungiku-kun won't tell us?
人斬りだ　なんでおめえがのうのうと生きてやがんだ！
Murderer...
Why are you still alive?
ちっ！ここは酒もねえのかよ！
Is there nothing to drink here?
おぉ 気が利くじゃねえか
Thanks.
生き返るぜ
This is great...
But there aren't any snacks with it.
だが つまみがねえな
お スルメ スルメ しかもゲソときちゃ酒が進むな
Oh! Squid.
Even tentacles... Those go great with sake.
What are you doing, new kid?
おい　新入り 何やってんだよ
Getting you out of there, of course!
もちろん恋川殿をここから出そうとしてます
おいおい バカなマネすんじゃねえ
Come on, don't be stupid.
They'll catch you, too!
お前も捕まるぞ
No, they won't!
いいえ 捕まりません
だって恋川殿はあのとき  強盗などやってないと言われてたじゃないですか
You said you aren't a thief!
So if I save you and you're innocent,
I won't have done anything wrong.
ならば 無罪の恋川殿を助けても  こっちには一切の非もありません
そもそも こんな牢に入れられる道理すらないのに
There's no reason to have you
jailed in the first place.
まったく皆さん なんて失礼な
How rude!
ほんとバカだぜ お前は
You really are dumb.
それ貸してみ
Give me that.
ノコギリで この切れ味
He cut clean through it with a saw?
今まで死ねと ののしる奴はたくさんいたが
A lot of people have cursed me.
お前みたいなのは 初めてだぜ
But I've never met anyone like you.
Kodenma Prison
何だ 今の音は
What was that noise?
大変です 恋川が脱獄を
Trouble! Koikawa's escaped!
刀も奪われました
He also took his sword!
なんだと！ 出あえ 出あえ！
What?
After him!
これからどうすんでえ
What do we do now?
Obviously, we find the real thief,
and give him to the magistrates.
もちろん 本当の下手人を捕まえて  火盗改の方々に差し出します
いくら恋川殿の無罪を訴えても 聞き入れてもらえませんでした
I told them you were innocent,
but they wouldn't listen.
だからなんとしても 下手人を捕らえ
And so, I want for them to...
恋川殿のことを 火盗改の…
いえ 江戸の皆さんに 信じてもらいたいんです
No, for all of Edo to believe in you.
弟子としては やはり 師匠が疑われているのは許せませんから
As your student...
I cannot allow my master to
be suspected of anything.
このたびの恋川春菊の不始末
Koikawa Shungiku's escape is my responsibility.
私の責任でございます
恋川の生い立ちですか
Koikawa's history?
かなり以前 報告いたしましたが
I gave it to you long ago...
とんでもない 蟲奉行様を愚弄するつもりなど
I meant absolutely no insult.
恋川は人斬りになるべくして生まれたと言っても 過言ではありません
You might say
that he was born to be a murderer.
Wanted: Koikawa Sanosuke
蟲奉行様も覚えていらっしゃいましょう
Do you remember the gang of thieves
that once operated in Edo: the Black Spiders?
一時期 江戸を騒がせた盗賊 黒蜘蛛組
Their leader was Koikawa Sanosuke,
and his son was Shungiku.
あの頭領 恋川左之助の息子が春菊です
人斬りができねえだぁ
You say you can't kill anyone?
俺たちゃ泣く子も黙る黒蜘蛛組だぞ
We are the Black Spiders. People fear us.
若頭がそれじゃ 俺たちもナメられちまいますよ
People won't think much of us
if our leader's son is such a wimp.
Shungiku, please don't be upset.
春菊 こらえておくれ
Okiku...
お菊 お前が甘やかすから
The reason my son
俺の息子は人斬りもできねえ意気地なしになっちまっただろうが
can't even kill a man is that you spoil him!
Killing is wrong.
人斬り 人斬りだけはしちゃいけないよ
You must never kill...
His mother, Okiku, was a kind woman,
far too good for Sanosuke.
母お菊は左之助には似合わぬ気立てのよい女でした
春菊はその血を受け継いだのでしょう
Shungiku must have inherited that trait from her.
数々の悪事に手を染めましたが
He committed many crimes,
but as his mother had asked,
母の言いつけを守って 人斬りだけはしませんでした
he never committed murder.
春菊　これは
Shungiku, this isn't—
若頭　若頭
Young master, our leader...
お頭は
あれほど　人斬りだけは
I asked you not to kill, so often...
母の言いつけを守れなかったこと
That he couldn't fulfill his mother's request,
followed by his mother's death...
そして　母の死
それが彼をおかしくしたのでしょう
It drove him mad.
父親左之助の後を追い
He followed in his father's footsteps,
killing any who stood in his way.
邪魔するものは誰であろうと切り捨てました
かつての仲間だろうが
Even former companions.
Or magistrates.
火付け盗賊改め方だろうが
Warrant: Koikawa Shungiku
見境なく
Anyone.
その数　九十九人
In all, ninety-nine died.
Thus, he became known as Koikawa Shungiku,
ゆえに　九十九斬りの恋川春菊と呼ばれるようになりました
Killer of 99.
いってしまったようですね
I think we lost them.
Yeah.
恋川殿はどのようにしてあのような美しい太刀筋を手に入れたんですか
Where did you learn such
beautiful swordsmanship?
唐突だろう　お前は
That's an odd question to ask right now.
I don't know.
知らねぇよ
ただ斬りまくっていたら　こうなっちまっただけだ
I just kept killing and this is how I ended up.
斬る？何をですか？
Killing? Killing what?
人を　だろ？
People...
Right?
九十九斬りの恋川春菊
The Killer of 99, Koikawa Shungiku.
まぁ　ちげぇねぇよな
Yeah, you got that right.
伊勢屋襲撃の下手人　その上脱獄とあらば切り捨てごめん
You stole at Iseya!
And since you've escaped from prison,
we can kill you here!
誤解です
It's not like that!
あれは恋川殿の仕業ではありません
Koikawa-dono didn't do it!
Shut up! He's a killer!
うるさい　そいつは人斬りだ
お前に殺された仲間の敵討ち　今果たさせてもらう
I'll avenge all of my
companions who you killed!
火盗改めのお仕事は下手人を捕まえること
The job of arson and theft
investigators is catching criminals.
切り殺すことではありません
It isn't to kill them!
うるさい　退け
Shut up!
And get out of the way!
Oogatana Kamakiri
Bladed Mantis
蟲だ
It's a bug!
剣が真っ二つ
It sliced my sword in two?
ここは春菊様に任しときな
Leave this one to me...
おめぇは火盗改めと一緒に町の人を逃がせ
You work with arson and theft
to evacuate the civilians.
はい
Right!
参りましょう　皆さん
Let's go, everyone!
仕方あるまい
We have no choice.
Koikawa!
恋川　今は見逃すが
We'll let you go for now,
but we'll kill you later!
後で必ず斬るからな
Forget that!
そんなことより　皆さんの避難を早く
We have to get everyone out of here!
大刀蟷螂が出ました　避難してください
A Bladed Mantis is here!
Please evacuate!
木戸番　木戸を開けよ
Doorman, open the gate!
私　走れないよ
I can't run...
町の人を守るのが蟲方の務め
Protecting the people is the
Insect Magistrate's job.
皆さん　こちらです
Everyone, this way!
ちょいまち
Wait just a second.
Now that I'm refreshed...
さーて　いっぱい引っ掛けたところで
Life's nothing but a drunken dream.
所詮人生なんざ酔った夢
And when you wake, you're dead!
覚めりゃ骸よ
そんなもんかよ
Is that all you have?
張りがいねぇな
Too easy.
Show yourself,
姿を見せろ　蜜月
Mitsuki.
やっぱりばれちゃった
So you noticed me, huh?
You're good, Mugai-kun.
さすが無涯君
It's been a long time.
お久しぶり　来ちゃった
I came to say hi.
ちょっと　しかと？
You're ignoring me?
お久しぶりなんだから　お話しようよ
It's been so long! Let's talk!
Hey! Hey! Has anything fun happened in Edo?
ねね　江戸でなんか楽しいことあった？
Any good date spots?
お勧めのデートスポットは？
好きな子とかできた？
Have you met a nice girl?
それからね　それからね
And... And...
何で無涯君はあたし達蟲狩りを裏切ったの？
Why did you betray us, the Insect Hunters?
You're so scary!
無涯君怖い
But we're finally about to get started.
でもね　あたし達もようやく行動に出るの
出始めは大刀蟷螂ちゃんかな
Our first target will be a Bladed Mantis.
だから　無涯君も戻ってきてくれるとうれしいなぁ
So we'd be happy if you'd come back.
お兄ちゃんも待ってるよ
Brother is waiting for you...
お前達…
You!
Now we'll just wait for the bug to kill you.
後は蟲が始末してくれる
You can go to hell alone, everyone has hated you!
お前なぞ恨まれたまま一人地獄に落ちるがいい
I have to fight humans before
I can fight that bug?
蟲の前に　人を相手かよ
I guess you can't sever karma's bonds.
結局　昔の縁は切れねぇってことか
溝みたいに真っ黒に汚れちまったこの手は
My hands are stained as black as the swamp.
All they can do
人を斬るしか　能がねぇんだな
is kill!
Move, kid!
退け　小僧
いいえ　退きません
No, I won't!
こいつが何をやったのか知っているのか
Do you know what he did?
What's wrong, Dad?
どうしたよ　親父　震えてるのか
Scared?
春　春菊君　聞いてくれ
Sh-Shungiku, hear me out.
It wasn't me...
俺じゃねぇ　お菊を殺したのは俺じゃねぇ
I didn't kill Okiku!
お父さんの言ってることは本当だよ
Your father speaks the truth.
A group known as the
Insect Hunters killed your mother.
君のお母さんを手にかけてたのは　蟲狩という連中だ
The Insect Hunters?
蟲狩？
Due to a mistake, that fool Koikawa
killed all those people!
愚かにも　恋川は勘違いから 人を殺し続けたんだ
Including my comrades!
我らの仲間もな
The past is the past and now is now!
昔は昔　今は今
太刀筋は嘘をつきません
His swordsmanship does not lie.
Please take a look at him now.
今の恋川殿をしかと見てください
His sword protects the people of Edo!
江戸の人達を守る斬撃です
The other one's yours, new kid.
新入り　そっちは任せた
Right!
はい　こいつはところてんですか
So is he jelly?
If a rock is konjac, then is he jelly?
いいえ　岩が蒟蒻なら　こいつはところてんですか
What you have to ask yourself is
how much you want to cut it.
ようは斬りてぇってどこまで思えるかだよ
Here I go, bug!
行くぜ　蟲ケラ
通った　恋川殿
It's working, Koikawa-dono!
その調子
Just like that!
Always be ready for a fight.
Always be ready for a fight!
常住戦陣
Plus Repentance Slash!
プラス　懺斬り
Don't think this atones for anything you did!
これで許されると思うなよ
お腹から小判
There was money in its stomach?
Hard to believe a bug was the robber...
まさか　蟲が下手人だったとはな
な　おめぇは何で俺があそこにいたか　 理由を知りたくねぇのか
Hey,
do you want to know why I was there?
If you couldn't tell them,
you must have had a very good reason!
それはやはり火盗改めの方々にも言えない深い理由があったのですね
深い理由ね
A good reason, huh?
A-Actually...
じ　実はよ   犬に襲われちまってな
I was attacked by a dog.
I've never liked dogs.
犬ってのがどうにも昔から苦手でよ
酔っ払って犬の尻尾を踏んじまったんだ
One day, I got drunk and stepped on a dog's tail.
So I ran away...
で　なんとか逃げ出して
And I grabbed the first thing I saw.
立ち上がりざまにそこら辺の物をつかんだら
死んだやつの刀で
It was a dead man's katana.
The rest is just as you saw it.
後はご覧の通りよ
But no one would believe
a stupid story like that.
やっぱこんなバカみてぇな話　誰も信じねぇよな
俺だって　こんなの聞かされたら　ぜってぇ信じねぇ
I know if someone had told me that story,
I'd never have believed it.
なるほど　それはとんだ災難でしたね
I see!
That must have been terrible...
He believes me!
って　信じてる
Okay! Let's go get drunk!
よし　兄ちゃん　今夜は飲もう
Right!
はい
兄ちゃん　おめぇはいいやつだ
You're a good guy, you know that?
Drink more.
もっと飲め
既におなかはがぼがぼですが
My stomach's already full, but...
師匠から進められた茶を 断るわけにはまいりません
I couldn't refuse the tea offered by my master.
はい
自分も恋川殿のような立派な武士になりたいのです
I want to be a great samurai like you.
武士？
Samurai?
I'm just a killer.
俺はただの人斬りさ
Next Time
Tenma-dono, I want to learn
天間殿の全力突っ張り
your Full-Power Slap!
自分も取り入れたいです
What kind of skill is that?
どんな技なんですか？
Tsukishima-style: Full-Power Slap!
月島流　全力突っ張り
Grab!
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回　蟲奉行
Ichinotani Tenma, I Can Do It!
「一乃谷天間　僕は出来る子！」
Ichinotani Tenma, I Can Do It